Guide to the Brooklyn Heights Garden Club Collection BCMS.0082
Brooklyn Collection
Brooklyn Heights Garden Club Collection
1940-2017
Brooklyn Collection
Brooklyn Heights Garden Club (Brooklyn Heights, New York, N.Y.)
BCMS.0082
4.8 Linear Feet in 6 boxes.
Documents, photographs, ephemera, clippings and scrapbooks documenting the history of the Brooklyn Heights Garden Club.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Brooklyn Heights Garden Club, 2019.
Historical Note
The Brooklyn Heights Garden Club was founded in 1940 by Mrs. Thomas Sturgis, who also served as the club's first president. The club was founded to "bring added beauty to Brooklyn Heights by the creation and cultivation of gardens, plantings and window boxes" and also sponsored a series of lectures. Over time, the club organized and aponsored a number of events and programs in the neighborhood and beyond. These include flower shows, plantings for the Brooklyn Heights Association house tour, trips to gardens around New York State, speaker events, flower arranging workshops, and the annual Christmas tree lighting at the Montague Street entrance to the Brooklyn Heights Promenade. The club has also participated in the Federated Garden Clubs of New York State (second district) and advocated for other related organizations in Brooklyn such as the Brooklyn Botanic Garden and Prospect Park. Traditionally, club meetings are held at members' homes, which fosters a sense of community among the membership. The club is still active as of 2021.
Arrangement
Materials are grouped in four series by type. In some cases, materials are grouped according to which member collected them and donated them to this collection. The Christmas tree scrapbooks and membership directories are arranged chronologically and the materials from other organizations are arranged alphabetically.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes documents, photographs, ephemera, clippings and scrapbooks dating from the club's founding in 1940 to 2017. Scrapbooks make up a significant portion of the collection and are especially rich in materials from the 1950s and 1960s. Photographs and ephemera make up smaller portions of the collection but there are some significant materials of each type, including flower show ribbons and candid photos of members at events. Between foldered documents and clippings and those found in the scrapbooks, the club's membership and activities over the years are well-documented in this collection.
Related Materials
Breukelen, Netherlands collection (2007.014)
Brooklyn Heights Association collection (ARC.148)
Brooklyn Heights Association Records (BCMS.0035)
Robert Vadheim Brooklyn Heights Association collection (1988.051)
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Gardens; Urban gardening; Federated Garden Clubs of New York State; Garden clubs
- Series 1: Club administration and membership
  - Constitution and by-laws, circa 1958-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Board and executive committee meeting notes and minutes, 1978-2015 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Meeting notes and attendance sheets, 1961-1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Meeting notes and attendance sheets, 1985-2008 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Presidents' reports, 1961-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Presidents' speeches, 1969-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Treasurers' reports, 1962-2008 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with membership, 1971-2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Meeting announcements and other correspondence from club officials to membership.
  - Club and member correspondence, 1960-2010 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Correspondence to and from individual club members or the club membership as a whole.
    General
    Additional correspondence can be found in the scrapbooks (Series 4).
  - Member lists and directories
    Additional member lists and directories for the years 1940, 1959-1960, 1962-1963, and 1964-1965 can be found in Scrapbook 1.
    - 1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 2006 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 2007-2008 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 2010 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 2011 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 2013-2014 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series 2: Events and programs
  - Photographs of club activities, 1961-2011 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Additional photographs can be found in the scrapbooks (Series 4).
  - Schedules of programs, 1969-1973, 1991-1999 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Additional program lists can be found in the scrapbooks (Series 4). Scrapbook 1: 1947-1950, 1957-1966 Scrapbook 2: 1966-1967, 1968-1973, 1975-1977
  - Event materials, 1940-2008 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes flyers, program ideas, and notes.
  - Speaker events, 1998-2003 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Flower shows, 1966-1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Flower show posters, circa 1986-1991 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Clem Kastiendieck flower show materials, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Flower arranging at St. Charles Jubilee Senior Center, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Cara Bowers program committee materials, 2007-2017 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Includes notes, documents, program ideas and ephemera, including meeting notes and treasurers' reports.
  - Pauline Herd Christmas tree lighting scrapbooks
    - 1949-1955 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1961 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1962 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1965 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1968 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1970 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1971 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 1972 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 1973 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - 1974 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - 1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - 1976 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - 1990-1999 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - 2000-2009 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Series 3: Clippings and ephemera
  Additional clippings and ephemera can be found in the scrapbooks (Series 4).
  - Clippings, circa 1973-2007 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Ephemera, 1950, 1990s (Box 4, Folder 10)
    "How to Conduct a Meeting" booklet, BHGC sticker, and card handed out during 1990 Brooklyn Heights house tour regarding tree gardens planted by club members.
  - Materials from other organizations
    - Brooklyn Botanic Garden, 1963-2001 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Brooklyn Center for the Urban Environment (BCUE), 1990-1994 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Federated Garden Clubs of New York State, 1986-2000 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Federated Garden Clubs of New York State, Second District, 1972-1996 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Kuykuit and Historic Hudson Valley, circa 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Prospect Park, 1977-1994 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Ephemera from various organizations, circa 1970-2000s (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Includes materials from Greenwood Cemetery, Governor's Island, Brooklyn Heights Association, Garden Club of Bay Ridge, Remsen Street/Montague Terrace Block Association, and others.
    - Gardening tips and resources, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series 4: Scrapbooks
  These scrapbooks include club member lists, clippings, photographs, ephemera (including ribbons from flower shows, flyers and other event materials), correspondence and program lists.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1940-1965 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1966-1995 (Box 6)